A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Eastern State Hospital Records, 1800-1876
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Eastern State Hospital Records, 1800-1876
The Library of Virginia
APA 128
4.65 cu. ft. (10 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
During its session begun in November 1769, the House of Burgesses passed an act establishing a hospital in Williamsburg for the mentally ill. The Eastern Lunatic Asylum (now Eastern State Hospital) was the first institution in America constructed as a mental hospital. The first patients were admitted in October 1773. By the mid 1960s the hospital had outgrown its location and moved west of Williamsburg. Today the hospital operates as a museum about the treatment of mental illness.
Scope and Content
Records, 1800-1876, including accounts and receipts, lists of patients, pay patient fund accounts, reports, vouchers, and warrants of the Eastern State Hospital located in Williamsburg, Virginia. The bulk of the records relate to the expenses for running and maintaining the hospital and inmates. The accounts and receipts and vouchers, 1803-1876, detail purchases of materials (timber, rail, nails), food (beef, veal, sugar, molasses, butter), salaries of the keepers and doctors, hire of slaves, transportation costs to jailers for bringing patients to the hospital, clothing, repairs to the building, purchase of furniture, and other sundry items. Of note are the oversize pay rolls, 1871 June-November, for officers and employees, including name, job title, and salary. There is much overlap between the accounts and receipts and vouchers so researchers should check all folders for pertinent information.
Of note are the lists of patients, 1800-1838, which include the patients name, residence, dates of commitment, and some include an inventory and estate value of patients. The Pay Patient Fund, 1858-1862, are accounts for those patients who paid for their own care at the hospital. Also of note are the Reports of the Board of Directors, 1823-1838, to the General Assembly. The reports include financial information as well as names of patients. Also included are warrants, 1858-1862, transferring money from the Auditor of Public Accounts to the hospital.
For additional information and records please see the Eastern State Hospital Records, 1770-2009 (LVA Accession 23459).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Accounts and receipts, 1803. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1804. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1805. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1806. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1807. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1808. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1809. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1810. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1811. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1812. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts, 1813. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Accounts and receipts, 1814. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1815. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1816. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1817. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1818. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1819. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1820. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1821. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1822. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1823. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts, 1824. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1825. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1826. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1827. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1828. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1829. (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1830. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1831. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1832. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1833. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1834. (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1835. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1836. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1837. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1838. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1839. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1840. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1841. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1842. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1844. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1845-1846. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1847. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1848. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts, 1849. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Accounts and receipts, 1850. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1851. (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1852. (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1853. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1854. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1855. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1856. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1857. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1858. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1861. (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1862. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1863. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1864-1865. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1866-1867. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1871. (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1872. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1873. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1876. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Auditors notes and memoranda, 1824-1849. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Lists of patients, 1800-1838. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Pay Patient Fund, Accounts and receipts, 1858. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Pay Patient Fund, Accounts and receipts, 1859. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Pay Patient Fund, Accounts and receipts, 1860. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Pay Patient Fund, Accounts and receipts, 1861. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Pay Patient Fund, Accounts and receipts, 1862. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Reports of the Director of the Lunatic Hospital, 1824-1838. (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Vouchers, 1806-1807. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Vouchers, 1822. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Vouchers, 1836. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Vouchers, 1836-1837. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Vouchers, 1837. (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
- Vouchers, 1837-1838. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Warrants, 1858-1860. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Warrants, 1861-1862. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Oversize, Accounts and receipts, 1805-1819. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Oversize, Accounts and receipts, 1820-1855. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Oversize, Accounts and receipts, 1857-1872. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Oversize, Lists of Patients, 1815-1838. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Oversize, Vouchers, 1806-1807. (Box 10, Folder 5)